<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dougal Matthews - blogofile</title><link href="http://www.dougalmatthews.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.dougalmatthews.com/feeds/tag/blogofile.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.dougalmatthews.com/</id><updated>2011-02-22T19:25:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Blogofile - rethinking simple websites</title><link href="http://www.dougalmatthews.com/2011/Feb/22/blogofile-rethinking-simple-websites/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-02-22T19:25:00+00:00</published><updated>2011-02-22T19:25:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Dougal Matthews</name></author><id>tag:www.dougalmatthews.com,2011-02-22:/2011/Feb/22/blogofile-rethinking-simple-websites/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This website has gone through a number of different solutions over the years
but during &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sitesprint.info/"&gt;SiteSprint&lt;/a&gt;(II) I settled on a new site built with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/montylounge/django-mingus"&gt;Mingus&lt;/a&gt;.
Mingus offers a great feature set and is really well made (it makes use of
many reusable apps that already exist). However, I was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This website has gone through a number of different solutions over the years
but during &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sitesprint.info/"&gt;SiteSprint&lt;/a&gt;(II) I settled on a new site built with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/montylounge/django-mingus"&gt;Mingus&lt;/a&gt;.
Mingus offers a great feature set and is really well made (it makes use of
many reusable apps that already exist). However, I was tired. Tired of
blogging platforms, I needed to go back to basics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, step up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.blogofile.com/"&gt;Blogofile&lt;/a&gt;. Firstly, what is it? Essentially it is a static
site generator. You get to use Python, a templating language and a fairly
simple but standard MVC architecture. However, the net result isn't a WSGI
Python app, but rather a static media. A whole set of HTML and your other
files like HTML and CSS too. One clever trick it uses is to take advantage of
folder structure and index.html files to create nice URL's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I use &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://disqus.com/"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; for all my comments the content of my blog rarely ever
changes. I add or update a post now and then but on a day to day basis, it
rarely changes. Rendering the page on each request is really inefficient and
caching each page is overkill. My CV for example is stored as markdown on my
site and rendered to html, a pdf or a doc as requested - now I only need to
do this once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the main advantage comes from editing almost everything in vim. Now if
I want to work on a post or do some maintenance I don't need to go through
the Django admin and work in there. I can simply edit in vim and push back
to the git repository. Which also means everything is version controlled and
maintained in a sane way which fits into my workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hosting isn't really an issue for me with Django as with tools like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://docs.fabfile.org/"&gt;Fabric&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/opscode/chef"&gt;Chef&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gunicorn.org/"&gt;Gunicorn&lt;/a&gt; it doesn't need to be painful anymore.
However, there is something to be said for the simplicity of deploying a
completely static site. I don't need to worry about a wsgi server, a database
or anything else and backing up isn't an issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have a few gripes with Blogfile though, they are fairly minor but
nothin' is perfect. I'm not a fan of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.makotemplates.org/"&gt;Mako&lt;/a&gt;, I'd much rather edit &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jinja.pocoo.org/"&gt;Jinja2&lt;/a&gt;
templates. I'm pondering adding this functionality and the nice thing about
blogofile is that it should be fairly straightforward to do so. When working
on your Blogofile site there is a handy server for testing locally but you
need to rebuild manually to see the changes. This is a little annoying and I
usually have two tabs open, one doing the rebuild every 10 seconds and one
serving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, you can see the code for my Blogofile Blog on
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/d0ugal/dm"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="python"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="blogofile"></category><category term="meta"></category></entry></feed>